<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "../../toolchain/docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd"
[
	<!ENTITY % local.common.attrib "xmlns:xi  CDATA  #FIXED 'http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'">
]>
<chapter>
	<title>Advanced Topics</title>
	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<para>This chapter covers a series of advanced topics.</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Routing</title>
		<para>
			MonoRail supports simple URL rewrites based on regular
			expressions. However, to use it for nicer URLs you must
			allow the ASP.NET ISAPI to handle all file extensions, which
			has a performance penalty.
		</para>
		<para>
			Another approach is to use an ISAPI filter that is able to
			rewrite URLs based on pattern matching.
			<ulink url="http://www.iismods.com">Mod_Rewrite</ulink>
			is one example of an ISAPI filter which performs URL
			rewriting. By using a ISAPI filter to rewrite URLs no
			wildcard mapping needs to be configured to direct all
			requests to the ASP.NET ISAPI. Even though the ASP.NET ISAPI
			will process requests for static files this is not ideal for
			a production site because of the performance penalty.
		</para>
		<para>
			Other URL rewriting solutions are available by different
			companies, some of them are free.
			<ulink url="http://www.isapirewrite.com/">
				ISAPI_Rewrite Lite
			</ulink>
			is one example.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>Configuration</title>
			<para>
				1 - Depending on how you intend to use routing will
				determine how it needs to be configured. If you will
				always be using filenames you only need map the specific
				extensions you want to work with (such as .aspx, .rails,
				.content, .article, etc). However, if you intend on
				routing directories (such as
				http://localhost/myapp/somedir/) then you will need to
				map everything (*.*) in IIS to aspnet_isapi.dll which
				causes IIS to redirect every request to the ASP.NET
				ISAPI (be aware of the consequences).
			</para>
			<para>
				2 - Create a
				<literal>routing</literal>
				element under the
				<literal>monorail</literal>
				element in your web.config as shown below. Routing rules
				will be evaluated in a top-down order until a match is
				found. If there are no matches the request will continue
				as normal with the requested URL.
			</para>
			<programlisting lang="html"><![CDATA[
<monorail>
	<routing>
		<rule>
			<pattern>(/blog/posts/)(\d+)/(\d+)/(.)*$</pattern>
			<replace><![CDATA[ /blog/view.rails?year=$2&month=$3 ]]]]]]><![CDATA[></replace>
		</rule>
		<rule>
			<pattern>(/news/)(\d+)/(\d+)/(.)*$</pattern>
			<replace><![CDATA[ /news/view.rails?year=$2&month=$3 ]]]]]]><![CDATA[></replace>
		</rule>
	</routing>
</monorail>
]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				3 - Add the routing module to the
				<literal>httpModules</literal>
				element of
				<literal>system.web</literal>
				in your web.config. Ensure that the routing module is
				listed before the monorail module as shown below.
			</para>
			<programlisting lang="html"><![CDATA[
	<system.web>
		<httpHandlers>
			<add verb="*" path="*.rails"
			  type="Castle.MonoRail.Engine.MonoRailHttpHandlerFactory, Castle.MonoRail.Engine" />
		</httpHandlers>
		
		<httpModules>
			<!-- NOTE: Routing MUST come before the monorail module -->
			<add name="routing" type="Castle.MonoRail.Framework.RoutingModule, Castle.MonoRail.Framework" />
			<add name="monorail" type="Castle.MonoRail.Framework.EngineContextModule, Castle.MonoRail.Framework" />
		</httpModules>
	</system.web>
]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				The regular expressions are compiled, therefore
				performance should be acceptable. If no matches are
				found then the request is processed as it would be
				without routing.
			</para>
			<para>
				This example routing rule defines that a request for the
				URL
				<literal>/blog/posts/2000/11/anything</literal>
				will be processed as if it was
				<literal>
					/blog/view.rails?year=2000&amp;month=11
				</literal>
				:
			</para>
			<programlisting lang="html"><![CDATA[
<pattern>(/blog/posts/)(\d+)/(\d+)/(.)*$</pattern>
<replace><![CDATA[ /blog/view.rails?year=$2&month=$3 ]]]]><![CDATA[></replace>
]]></programlisting>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Root Directory Mapping Workaround</title>
			<para>
				If you do not want to setup a wildcard mapping just to
				get a default document for your root directory you can
				use these steps:
			</para>
			<para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							Create an empty file in your root directory
							that is mapped to aspnet_isapi.dll and is a
							configured as a default document in IIS. For
							example, create a file named index.rails or
							default.aspx depending on your
							configuration.
						</para>
					</listitem>

					<listitem>
						<para>
							Then create a new routing rule in your
							web.config as shown below.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
			<programlisting lang="html"><![CDATA[
	<monorail>
		<routing>
			<rule>
				<pattern>^(/index.rails)(.)*$</pattern>
				<replace><![CDATA[ /Controller/Action.rails?$2 ]]]]><![CDATA[></replace>
			</rule>
		</routing>
	</monorail>
]]></programlisting>
			<note>
				<para>
					This work around is only feasible for root
					directories because the default document file must
					be created in each directory which is not practical
					for URLs that contain dynamic strings.
				</para>
			</note>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Another Approach</title>
			<para>
				David Moore has sent an interesting approach he uses:
			</para>
			<para>
				"I really like mod_rewrite, but as you can see it
				requires 3rd party components also.
			</para>
			<para>
				The easiest thing is to use what you already have at
				your fingertips with IIS, ASP.NET and MonoRail itself,
				and route all requests through ASP.NET. Then, you can
				use the MonoRail URL rewriting features within
				web.config.
			</para>
			<para>
				Now performance-wise, you don't want to route requests
				through the ASP.NET/MonoRail stack for things such as
				.css files, image resources etc. What I do for this is
				that I map the URLs for all static resources to another
				virtual directory which is purely IIS serving up these
				files.
			</para>
			<para>
				I.e. I make the $static variable available in all my
				NVelocity templates, and if I insert an image it looks
				like this: &lt;img src="$static/images/image.gif"/&gt;
				as a simple example.
			</para>
			<para>
				This currently resolves to
				http://localhost/static/images/image.gif, with /static
				being a virtual directory, and within there all my
				static content (css, javascript, images etc).
			</para>
			<para>
				This is very scalable in that in a production
				environment, we can change our $static to point to
				http://static.ourdomain.com and have light and fast web
				servers such as lighttpd or just a vanilla IIS serving
				up our static content fast, easing the load on a
				dedicated application server.
			</para>
			<para>
				So in summary, I evaluated mod_rewrite-style
				alternatives and went with the simple solution built
				into MonoRail, and implemented a good practice of having
				a separate URL for static content which is going to make
				our application more scalable in the future anyway."
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Additional Information</title>
			<para>
				Josh wrote a very interesting post about MonoRail and
				<ulink
					url="http://joshrobb.com/blog/2007/04/26/monorail-url-rewriting/">
					Url rewriting
				</ulink>
				.
			</para>
			<para>
				Colin Ramsay wrote about
				<ulink
					url="http://colinramsay.co.uk/2007/04/17/url-rewriting-options-on-iis/">
					rewriting options for IIS
				</ulink>
				.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Caching Support</title>

		<para></para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Transformation Filters</title>
		<para>
			Transformation Filters allow you to manipulate the stream of
			data that defines a generated page before it is sent to the
			client.
		</para>
		<para>
			Right before a generated page is streamed to the client, you
			can use a Transformation Filter to manipulate the stream.
			The Transformation Filter is applied
			<emphasis>after</emphasis>
			the view engine has built the page. Your view engine is not
			used with a Transformation Filter.
		</para>
		<para>
			To assign a Transformation Filter to an action, use the
			TransformationFilter attribute.
		</para>
		<programlisting lang="cs"><![CDATA[
public class UserController : Controller
{
	[TransformationFilter(typeof(UpperCaseTransformationFilter))]
    public void View()
    {
    }
}
]]></programlisting>
		<para>
			In the example above, the entire page generated by the View
			action will be converted to upper case text.
		</para>
		<para>
			You may apply multiple Transformation Filters to an action.
			To control their order of execution, use the ExecutionOrder
			property.
		</para>
		<programlisting lang="cs"><![CDATA[
public class UserController : Controller
{
	[TransformFilter(typeof(WikiTransformFilter), ExecutionOrder=1), TransformFilter(typeof(UpperCaseTransformFilter), ExecutionOrder=2)]
	public void View()
    {
    }
}
]]></programlisting>
		<para>
			In the example above, the page generated by the View action
			will first be transformed using the WikiTransformFilter and
			then the result of that will be transformed to upper case
			text.
		</para>
		<para>
			You can create your own Transformation Filters by inheriting
			from the TransformFilter abstract base class.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Dynamic Actions</title>
		<para>
			Dynamic actions and action providers are a way to create
			custom and dynamic functionality.
		</para>
		<note>
			<para>
				A sample demonstrating the concepts in the section can
				be downloaded from
				!download/monorail/trunk/MonoRail.DynActProvSample.zip
			</para>
		</note>
		<para>
			MonoRail considers every public instance method of a
			controller an action, for certain situations this is not
			enough. For example, you want to decide on the name for a
			section in the URL at runtime when the data is available; or
			a set of controllers that inherit from a distinct common
			super class need the same action which can be defined in the
			super class.
		</para>
		<para>
			Dynamic Actions are a way to associate code with a name in
			runtime.
		</para>
		<para>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/Dyn-action.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</para>
		<para>
			A dynamic action is nothing more than an implementation of
			the interface
			<literal>IDynamicAction</literal>
			:
		</para>
		<programlisting lang="cs"><![CDATA[
public interface IDynamicAction
{
    /// <summary>
    /// Implementors should perform the action 
    /// upon this invocation
    /// </summary>
    void Execute(Controller controller);
}
]]></programlisting>
		<para>
			You can associate a dynamic action with a controller using
			the
			<literal>DynamicActions</literal>
			property:
		</para>
		<programlisting lang="cs"><![CDATA[
public class MyController : Controller
{
    public MyController
    {
        DynamicActions["index"] = new IndexDynamicAction();
    }
}
]]></programlisting>
		<section>
			<title>Dynamic Action Providers</title>
			<para>
				Dynamic Action Providers are in charge of adding dynamic
				actions to controllers. They can be associated with
				controllers using the
				<literal>DynamicActionAttribute</literal>
				:
			</para>
			<programlisting lang="cs"><![CDATA[
[DynamicAction(typeof(MyDynActionProvider))]
public class MyController : Controller
{
    public MyController
    {
    }
}
]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				The implementation of the provider can be something
				static (ie. always add the same set of actions) or can
				"read" something from the controller or the logged user;
				and add the actions accordingly:
			</para>
			<programlisting lang="cs"><![CDATA[
public class MyDynActionProvider : IDynamicActionProvider
{
    public void IncludeActions(Controller controller)
    {
        controller.DynamicActions["index"] = new IndexDynamicAction();
    }
}
]]></programlisting>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Scaffolding</title>
		<para>
			Scaffolding is a idea borrowed from
			<ulink
				url="http://wiki.rubyonrails.org/rails/pages/Scaffold">
				Ruby on Rails
			</ulink>
			. It refers to the ability to create pages with a simple
			interface to data in a database with very little effort.
		</para>
		<para>
			As every project under the Castle Project umbrella does not
			obligate you to embrace it all, scaffolding is implemented
			with the
			<literal>IScaffoldingSupport</literal>
			interface.
		</para>
		<para>
			MonoRail will instantiate the implementation specificed if
			it discovers a controller with one or more
			<literal>ScaffoldingAttribute</literal>
			:
		</para>
		<programlisting lang="cs"><![CDATA[
[Scaffolding(typeof(Blog))]
public class BlogsController : Controller
{
    public BlogsController()
    {
    }
}
]]></programlisting>
		<para>
			The scaffolding implementor should register actions as a
			dynamic action provider.
		</para>
		<para>
			The default implementation of scaffolding support relies on
			Castle ActiveRecord and is discussed in the
			<ulink url="../integration/arscaffold.html">
				integrations documentation section
			</ulink>
			.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Extensions</title>
		<para>
			From MonoRail beta 5 you can use the new Extensions support
			which allow you to plug existing extensions or develop your
			own extensions. This document should clarify why extensions
			were introduced, a list of out-of-box extensions and how to
			create your own extensions.
		</para>
		<para>
			The user and development community on MonoRail is quite
			active, and consequently we receive lots of suggestion about
			new interesting features. Some of the features are
			unarguably helpful for the almost every user, however most
			of them are only useful to some specific users/scenarios. So
			implementing the new feature directly into the core
			framework would not make much sense as they usually increase
			the request flow overhead and the users that are not using
			the feature would be penalized.
		</para>
		<para>
			Extensions were introduced to allow the framework to be
			extended easily and extensions to be reused.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>Creating Custom Extensions</title>
			<para>
				Creating an extension is a fairly simple task. Just
				create a new public class and implement the
				IMonoRailExtension or extend from
				AbstractMonoRailExtension. The latter is simpler.
			</para>
			<para>
				After that you can override the methods you want.
				Usually your extension will read some custom
				configuration from the MonoRailConfiguration to
				configure itself if necessary and then perform some
				action when one of the hook methods is invoked.
			</para>
			<para>
				MonoRail must be told that an extension exists. You can
				do that by using the extensions node in the
				configuration file. For more on that, check the
				<ulink url="../manual/configurationref.html">
					MonoRail Configuration Reference
				</ulink>
				document.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Built In Extensions</title>
			<para>
				With the beta 5 version we shipped two extensions. As
				they can be helpful for some scenarios, they were also
				developed to serve as sample extensions, so the code is
				very simple.
			</para>
			<xi:include href="extensions/custom_session.xml" />
			<xi:include href="extensions/exception_chaining.xml" />
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Service Architecture</title>
		<para>
			It's impossible to come up with a sophisticated software
			where the default behavior pleases everyone and integrates
			with everything. The usual solution is making the software
			rely on contracts and having the core code as just a
			coordination of invocations on the contracts implementation.
			An user is thus capable of replacing one or more contract
			implementation.
		</para>
		<para>
			The challenging is implementing an architecture where the
			parts are easily replaced, configurable and can rely
			(depend) on other parts.
		</para>
		<para>
			MonoRail uses a set of services to handle specific tasks.
			The framework is responsible for defining the default
			implementations, instantiate, start and configure them. The
			services are made available through a combination of
			lifecycle interfaces and an implementation of
			<literal>IServiceProvider</literal>
		</para>
		<para>
			The most usual solution to this problem is to use an
			Inversion of Control container. However, things have to be
			balanced. For MonoRail, an IoC container would introduce
			dependencies on assemblies and an longer initialization. In
			the end, we wouldn't benefit from all IoC container
			features, so it could be considered too much for our
			problem.
		</para>
		<para>
			Instead, we combined what is already on the .Net library and
			some creative solution.
		</para>
		<para>
			Basically we create two levels of services registries, per
			application and per request, and a simple interfaces that
			defines lifecycles that services optionally implement. This
			allow the service to start its work when it is supposed to
			and to gather reference to other services.
		</para>
		<section>
			<title>How It Works</title>

			<para>
				When the web application is started, the ASP.Net modules
				are initialized. MonoRail has a
				<literal>EngineContextModule</literal>
				which is in charge of
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Read the configuration</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>Initialize the services</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Subscribe to ASP.Net application and request
						level events
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Create a request context (which we'll not cover
						here)
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			<para>
				Services implementation can be defined in the
				configuration section. After reading the configuration
				section MonoRail checks for missing definition and
				register the missing services using the default
				implementation.
			</para>
			<para>
				After that it instantiates every service and runs the
				lifecycle. If everything went well, the framework is
				properly initialized. All services are registered in the
				application level container, which happens to be
				implemented by the
				<literal>EngineContextModule</literal>
				class. We call this the parent container.
			</para>
			<para>
				When a request starts, MonoRail creates a
				<literal>DefaultRailsEngineContext</literal>
				instance, which also is a container for services.
				MonoRail sets the parent container on it. This allow the
				user to override services per request, and resolution of
				services in the parent.
			</para>
			<para>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</para>
			<para>
				<orderedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							The configuration is read into the
							<literal>MonoRailConfiguration</literal>
							. It's also registered as a service
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							The services collected are instantiated and
							registered
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>The lifecycle is executed</para>
					</listitem>
				</orderedlist>
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Lifecycle Interfaces</title>
			<para>
				A service might implement a few interfaces to expose to
				MonoRail that it behaves in a specific way or that it
				needs something from the framework.
			</para>
			<para>
				<emphasis>
					ISupportInitialize (from System.ComponentModel)
				</emphasis>
			</para>
			<para>
				This interface can be implemented if a service wants
				performs some initialization.
			</para>
			<para>
				<emphasis>IInitializable (from Castle.Core)</emphasis>
			</para>
			<para>
				This interface can be implemented if a service wants
				performs some initialization.
			</para>
			<para>
				<emphasis>
					IServiceEnabledComponent (from Castle.Core)
				</emphasis>
			</para>
			<para>
				This interface can be implemented if a service uses
				other services.
			</para>
			<para>
				<literal>IServiceEnabledComponent</literal>
				is the first one to be invoked. This gives a chance to
				services gather all services references it wants. Then
				the initialization interface's methods are invoked.
			</para>
			<para>
				For service that uses
				<literal>IServiceEnabledComponent</literal>
				lifecycle, the implementor should keep in mind that the
				initialization lifecycle has not run for all services,
				so it might not be safe to use other services as they
				might not be properly initialized at the moment.
			</para>
			<para>
				The order of service registration and instantiation is
				not guaranted. So the implementor should not make any
				assumption regarding it.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Registering Services</title>
			<para>
				You have to use the
				<literal>monorail</literal>
				configuration node to override or add services to
				MonoRail.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Built-In Services</title>
			<para>
				The following is a succint list of services and their
				roles. You can refer to this list to learn more about
				MonoRail inner workings or to use them when developing
				extensions and new services.
			</para>
			<section>
				<title><literal>MonoRailConfiguration</literal></title>
				<para>Exposes the MonoRail configuration</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title><literal>ExtensionManager</literal></title>
				<para>
					Manages registered extensions dispatching events
					from Asp.Net infrastructure and from MonoRail
					services
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title><literal>IViewSourceLoader</literal></title>
				<para>
					Sits in front of the file system and from assembly
					resources. It is used by view engines to obtain view
					streams
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title><literal>IViewEngine</literal></title>
				<para>Process view templates</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title><literal>IScaffoldingSupport</literal></title>
				<para>Adds scaffold support to a controller</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title><literal>IControllerFactory</literal></title>
				<para>Creates the controller instances</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title><literal>IViewComponentFactory</literal></title>
				<para>
					Manages registered ViewComponents and creates their
					instances
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title><literal>IFilterFactory</literal></title>
				<para>
					Manages registered filters and creates their
					instances
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title><literal>IResourceFactory</literal></title>
				<para>Create resources</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title><literal>IEmailSender</literal></title>
				<para>Sends e-mail</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title><literal>IEmailTemplateService</literal></title>
				<para>
					Process e-mail templates using the MonoRail
					infrastructure
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title><literal>IControllerDescriptorProvider</literal></title>
				<para>
					Inspects Controller types building a descriptor of
					what has been defined using attributes
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title><literal>IResourceDescriptorProvider</literal></title>
				<para>
					Creates descriptors for resources declared on
					controllers
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title><literal>IRescueDescriptorProvider</literal></title>
				<para>
					Creates descriptors for rescues declared on
					controllers
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title><literal>ILayoutDescriptorProvider</literal></title>
				<para>
					Creates descriptors for layouts declared on
					controllers
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title><literal>IHelperDescriptorProvider</literal></title>
				<para>
					Creates descriptors for helpers declared on
					controllers
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title><literal>IFilterDescriptorProvider</literal></title>
				<para>
					Creates descriptors for filters declared on
					controllers
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title><literal>IControllerTree</literal></title>
				<para>
					Manages a binary tree of controllers registered
				</para>
			</section>
			<section>
				<title><literal>ICacheProvider</literal></title>
				<para>Manages the cache</para>
			</section>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Custom Bindable Parameters</title>
		<para>
			When an action is invoked on a controller that extends
			<literal>SmartDispatcherController</literal>
			, it inspects the parameters for attributes that implement
			<literal>IParameterBinder</literal>
			. The
			<literal>DataBindAttribute</literal>
			for exemple is one of these attributes.
		</para>
		<para>
			This allow you to create binding logic, or add validation or
			anything that you want. You just need to create an attribute
			that applies to method arguments and implements the
			<literal>IParameterBinder</literal>
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Using Resources to Store Views</title>
		<para>
			Aside from the file system you can have views on the
			resource assemblies. This feature was introduced due to a
			necessity to reuse controllers, filters and views among
			projects, for example an user administration module.
		</para>
		<para>
			To configure the assemblies that have views, use the
			<literal>additionalSources</literal>
			configuration node. See
			<ulink url="../manual/configurationref.html">
				MonoRail Configuration Reference
			</ulink>
			document.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Enabling Logging</title>
		<para>
			You can supply an implementation of
			<literal>ILoggingFactory</literal>
			so MonoRail can use logger for its internal pieces and allow
			you to use the
			<literal>Controller.Logger</literal>
			.
		</para>
		<para>
			Use the services node with the key
			<literal>Custom</literal>
			. The example below uses log4net. Make sure you have a
			<literal>log4net.config</literal>
			on the root directory that configures log4net.
		</para>
		<programlisting lang="html"><![CDATA[
<monorail>
	
	<services>
		<service 
			id="Custom" 
			interface="Castle.Core.Logging.ILoggerFactory, Castle.Core"
			type="Castle.Services.Logging.Log4netIntegration.Log4netFactory, Castle.Services.Logging.Log4netIntegration" />
	</services>
	
	...
]]></programlisting>
	</section>
</chapter>